If you can't see a better future, build one.
Megalopolis is a science fiction, drama, fantasy
film directed by Francis Ford Coppola.
In a futuristic New York known as New Rome, visionary architect Cesar Catilina dreams of
building "Megalopolis," a utopian city that redefines society’s limits.
Opposing him is the corrupt Mayor Franklyn Cicero,
who clings to power and profit.
Between them stands Julia, the mayor’s daughter, whose love for Cesar forces her
to choose between loyalty, ambition, and the fate of humanity.
Cesar Catilina, played by Adam Driver.
Mayor Cicero, played by Giancarlo Esposito.
Julia Cicero, played by Nathalie Emmanuel.
Wow Platinum, played by Aubrey Plaza.
Clodio Pulcher, played by Shia LaBeouf.
Hamilton Crassus III, played by Jon Voight.
Megalopolis is a 2024 American epic science fiction drama film
written, directed, and produced by Francis Ford Coppola.
The film features an ensemble cast including Adam Driver, Giancarlo Esposito, Nathalie Emmanuel, Aubrey Plaza, Shia LaBeouf, Jon
Voight, Laurence Fishburne, Talia Shire, Jason Schwartzman, Kathryn Hunter, Grace VanderWaal, Chloe Fineman, James Remar, D.
Sweeney, and Dustin Hoffman.
Set in an alternate 21st-century New York City (restyled "New Rome"), the film follows visionary architect Cesar Catilina (Driver) as he clashes with the
corrupt Mayor Franklyn Cicero (Esposito), who opposes Catilina's plans to revitalize New Rome by building the futuristic utopia "Megalopolis".
The film draws on Roman history, particularly the Catilinarian conspiracy of 63
BC and the decay of the Roman Republic into the Roman Empire.
In 1977, Coppola had the idea to make a film drawing parallels between the fall of the Roman Republic and
the future of the United States by retelling the Catilinarian conspiracy in modern New York.
Although he began plotting the film in 1983, the
project spent decades in development hell.
Coppola attempted to produce the film in 1989 and again in 2001, but each time, the studios refused to finance the film, due
to Coppola's string of late-career box-office disappointments and the September 11 attacks, respectively.
Disillusioned by the studio system, Coppola did not produce Megalopolis
until he built a large fortune in the winemaking business.
He spent $120 million of his own money to make the film.
Principal photography took place in Georgia from November 2022 to March 2023.
The film reunited Coppola with past collaborators, including actors Esposito, Fishburne, Remar, Shire, and Sweeney,
cinematographer Mihai Mălaimare Jr., composer Osvaldo Golijov, and Coppola's son, second-unit director Roman Coppola.
Like several other Coppola films, Megalopolis had a troubled production.
Coppola adopted an experimental style, encouraging his actors to improvise and write certain
scenes during the shoot, and adding his own last-minute changes to the script.
Members of the art department and visual effects team, among
others, left or were fired from the film.
Megalopolis was selected to compete for the Palme d'Or at the 77th Cannes
Film Festival, but polarized critics and Hollywood studios.
Coppola could not find a studio that would both reimburse his
production costs and pay for a large marketing campaign.
He opted to pay for an advertising campaign, with Lionsgate
theatrically releasing the film in the United States.
It endured a troubled run-up to release: a trailer was removed for using fabricated pull quotes, and Coppola sued
trade publication Variety for libel after it published allegations of sexual misconduct by him on set.
The film premiered at Cannes on May 16, 2024, and was
released theatrically on September 27, 2024.
It was a commercial failure, grossing $14.3 million
against a budget of $120 to $136 million.
Reviews were mixed, with some critics praising the film's ambition and
style while many critics found it chaotic and uneven.
Critics were also greatly polarized on the acting and story.
The film explores themes of new year's eve,
infidelity, suicide, widow, wedding reception.
The tone is emotional and thought_provoking and mind_bending.